BETH: Sensory overload happens when there
is more input from the five senses than
a brain can sort through and process.
These could be; multiple
conversations, flashing overhead
lights, lots of music or loud noise.
In most people the brain prioritises
what sensory information to focus
on, but with individuals in autism
this is not straightforward.
JOE: Individuals with autism may find
this more of a problem because they may
suffer from hypersensitivity and therefore
things that might not normally cause
sensory overload can seem much worse.
Their brain focusses on something
such as a buzzing sound and sends
a message to get away from it.
The body then starts to panic,
and a chain reaction can start.
Sensory overload in people with autism
can mean focusing on the smallest most
insignificant thing over other things.
It may be flashing lights,
a fluffy carpet, marks on a
wall, or even a strong smell.
BETH: Symptoms of sensory overload
may vary but some common ones include
difficulty focusing, extreme irritability
or restlessness and discomfort.
An individual may need to cover
their eyes or ears to shield
themselves from any sensory input.
They may become agitated and stressed
about their surrounding and their
sensitivity to other things may increase.
Eventually sensory overload can
cause extreme stress and anxiety,
physical pain and distressed behaviour
which may develop into a meltdown.